The youthful perspective on the future,
Mlad pogled na budućnost,
the present perspective on the future
sadašnji pogled na budućnost
and the future, mature perspective on the future --
i budući, zreo pogled na budućnost --
I'd like to try and bring all those three tenses together
Večeras ću pokušati povezati ta tri glagolska vremena
in one identity tonight.
u jedan identitet.
And you could say that the poet, in many ways,
Možemo reći da pjesnik na mnoge načine
looks at what I call "the conversational nature of reality."
razmatra "razgovornu prirodu stvarnosti".
And you ask yourself:
Pitate se:
What is the conversational nature of reality?
Što je razgovorna priroda stvarnosti?
The conversational nature of reality is the fact
Razgovorna je priroda stvarnosti
that whatever you desire of the world --
činjenica da što god želite od svijeta --
whatever you desire of your partner in a marriage or a love relationship,
što god želite od bračnog partnera ili ljubavne veze,
whatever you desire of your children,
što god želite od svoje djece,
whatever you desire of the people who work for you or with you,
što god želite od ljudi koji rade za vas ili s vama,
or your world --
ili od vašeg svijeta...
will not happen exactly as you would like it to happen.
ne ostvaruje se onako kako biste vi to voljeli.
But equally,
Jednako tako,
whatever the world desires of us --
što god svijet želi od nas --
whatever our partner, our child, our colleague,
što god naš partner, naše dijete, naš kolega,
our industry,
naša industrija,
our future demands of us,
naša budućnost zahtijeva od nas,
will also not happen.
jednako se tako neće ostvariti.
And what actually happens
Ono što se ostvaruje
is this frontier between what you think is you
jest granica između onoga što mislite da vi jeste
and what you think is not you.
i što mislite da niste.
And this frontier of actual meeting
A ta granica stvarnog susreta
between what we call a self and what we call the world
između onoga što zovemo bićem i onoga što zovemo svijetom
is the only place, actually, where things are real.
zapravo je jedino mjesto na kojem se događa stvarnost.
But it's quite astonishing,
No zapanjujuće je
how little time we spend at this conversational frontier,
kako malo vremena trošimo na toj razgovornoj granici,
and not abstracted away from it in one strategy or another.
kada nismo odvojeni od nje drugim strategijama.
I was coming through immigration,
Prošle godine prolazio sam kroz imigracijsku kontrolu,
which is quite a dramatic border at the moment,
što je danas jedna vrlo dramatična granica,
into the US last year,
da bih ušao u SAD,
and, you know, you get off an international flight
i prošli ste međunarodni let
across the Atlantic,
preko Atlantskog oceana,
and you're not in the best place;
i ne osjećate se baš najbolje,
you're not at your most spiritually mature.
niste baš duhovno zreli.
You're quite impatient with the rest of humanity, in fact.
Zapravo, nemate baš strpljenja za druge.
So when you get up to immigration with your shirt collar out
I kada dođete do imigracijske sa zgužvanim ovratnikom
and a day's growth of beard,
i jednodnevnom bradom,
and you have very little patience,
nemate baš strpljenja,
and the immigration officer looked at my passport
a imigracijski službenik pogleda putovnicu
and said, "What do you do, Mr. Whyte?"
i upita: "Čime se bavite, g. Whyte?"
I said, "I work with the conversational nature of reality."
Rekao sam "Bavim se razgovornom prirodom stvarnosti."
(Laughter)
(Smijeh)
And he leaned forward over his podium
Nagnuo se preko pulta
and he said, "I needed you last night."
i rekao "Dobro biste mi došli sinoć".
(Laughter)
(Smijeh)
(Applause)
(Pljesak)
And I said, "I'm sorry,
Odgovorio sam "Žao mi je,
my powers as a poet and philosopher only go so far.
kao pjesnik i filozof, imam ograničene mogućnosti.
I'm not sure I can --"
Nisam siguran da mogu --"
But before we knew it,
I prije nego što smo se snašli,
we were into a conversation about his marriage.
razgovarali smo o njegovom braku.
Here he was in his uniform,
Stajao je tamo u svojoj odori,
and the interesting thing was,
i što je najzanimljivije,
he was looking up and down the row of officers
stalno je pogledavao u ostale službenike
to make sure his supervisor didn't see
kako bi se uvjerio da njegov nadređeni
that we was having a real conversation.
ne vidi da vodi stvaran razgovor.
But all of us live at this conversational frontier
No svi mi živimo na toj razgovornoj granici
with the future.
prema budućnosti.
I'd like to put you in the shoes of my Irish niece,
Želim vam predstaviti pogled svoje irske nećakinje
Marlene McCormack,
Marlene McCormack,
standing on a cliff edge on the western coast of Spain,
koja stoji na rubu litice na zapadnoj obali Španjolske
overlooking the broad Atlantic.
i gleda u veliki Atlantski ocean.
Twenty-three years old, she's just walked 500 miles
Ima dvadeset i tri godine i upravo je propješačila 800 km
from Saint Jean Pied de Port on the French side of the Pyrenees,
od Saint Jean Pied de Porta na francuskoj strani Pireneja,
all the way across Northern Spain,
preko cijele sjeverne Španjolske,
on this very famous, old and contemporary pilgrimage
na poznatom, starom i suvremenom,
called the Camino de Santiago de Compostela --
hodočašću Camino de Santiago de Compostela --
the Path to Santiago of Compostela.
Put do Santiaga de Compostele.
And when you get to Santiago, actually,
A kada dođete do Santiaga,
it can be something of an anticlimax,
možete doživjeti antiklimaks,
because there are 100,000 people living there
jer tamo živi 100.000 ljudi
who are not necessarily applauding you as you're coming into town.
koji vam ne salutiraju kada dođete u grad.
(Laughter)
(Smijeh)
And 10,000 of them are trying to sell you a memento of your journey.
A njih 10.000 pokušava vam prodati uspomenu na putovanje.
But you do have the possibility of going on for three more days
Ali imate mogućnost nastaviti još tri dana
to this place where Marlene stood, called, in Spanish, Finisterre,
do tog mjesta gdje je Marlene stajala, na španjolskom se zove Finisterre,
in English, Finisterre,
i na engleskom Finisterre,
from the Latin, meaning "the ends of the earth,"
iz latinskog, što znači "rubovi zemlje",
the place where ground turns to ocean;
mjesto gdje se zemlja pretvara u ocean;
the place where your present turns into the future.
mjesto gdje se sadašnjost pretvara u budućnost.
And Marlene had walked this way --
I Marlene je propješačila do tamo --
she just graduated as a 23-year-old from the University of Sligo
23-godišnjakinja koja je na Sveučilištu u Sligu
with a degree in Irish drama.
diplomirala irsku dramu,
And she said to me, "I don't think the major corporations of the world
rekla mi je "Ne vjerujem da će me velike svjetske korporacije
will be knocking on my door."
tražiti."
I said, "Listen, I've worked in corporations all over the world
Rekao sam "Slušaj, radio sam za korporacije diljem svijeta
for decades;
desetljećima;
a degree in drama is what would most prepare you for the adult --
studij drame najbolje te priprema za odrasli --
(Laughter)
(Smijeh)
corporate world."
korporativni svijet."
(Applause)
(Pljesak)
But she said, "I'm not interested in that, anyway.
Ali rekla je: "To me ionako ne zanima.
I don't want to teach drama, I want to become a dramatist.
Ne želim predavati dramu, želim postati dramaturginja.
I want to write plays.
Želim pisati drame.
So I walked the Camino in order to give myself some courage,
Prošla sam Camino da bih se ohrabrila,
in order to walk into my future."
da bih išla prema svojoj budućnosti."
And I said, "What was the most powerful moment you had on the whole Camino,
Pitao sam: "Koji ti je bio najmoćniji trenutak u Caminu,
the very most powerful moment?"
onaj baš najsnažniji trenutak?"
She said, "I had many powerful moments,
Rekla je: "Doživjela sam mnoge snažne trenutke,
but you know, the most powerful moment was post-Camino,
ali onaj najmoćniji je kada prođeš Camino,
was the three days you go on from Santiago and come to this cliff edge.
ona tri dana kada prođeš Santiago i dođeš do ruba litice.
And you go through three rituals.
Prolaziš kroz tri rituala.
The first ritual is to eat a tapas plate of scallops" --
Prvi je pojesti platu kapica" --
or if you're vegetarian,
ili ako ste vegetarijanac,
to contemplate the scallop shell.
diviti se školjkama kapica.
(Laughter)
(Smijeh)
Because the scallop shell has been the icon and badge of your walk,
Ipak su školjke kapica postale simbol hodočašća
and every arrow that you have seen along that way
i sve strelice duž puta
has been pointing underneath a scallop shell.
prikazane su ispod školjki kapica.
So really, this first ritual is saying:
Stoga se prvi ritual sastoji od pitanja:
How did you get to this place?
Kako sam došao ovamo?
How did you follow the path to get here?
Koji sam put slijedio da bih došao?
How do you hold the conversation of life when you feel unbesieged,
Kako razmišljaš o životu kada se osjećaš neopsjednut,
when you're unbullied,
nenapadnut,
when you're left to yourself?
kada si prepušten sebi?
How do you hold the conversation of life that brings you to this place?
Kako razmišljaš o životu koji te doveo ovamo?
And the second ritual is that you burn something that you've brought.
A drugi je ritual spaliti nešto što si donio sa sobom.
I said, "What did you burn, Marlene?"
Pitao sam: "Što si spalila, Marlene?"
She said, "I burned a letter and two postcards."
Rekla je: "Spalila sam pismo i dvije razglednice."
I said, "Astonishing.
Rekao sam: "Zapanjujuće.
Twenty-three years old and you have paper.
Imaš dvadeset i tri godine i uza sebe papir.
I can't believe it."
Ne mogu vjerovati."
(Laughter)
(Smijeh)
I'm sure there's a Camino app
Siguran sam da postoji aplikacija za Camino
where you can just delete a traumatic text, you know?
u kojoj možeš jednostavno izbrisati traumatičnu poruku.
(Laughter)
(Smijeh)
It will engage the flashlight,
Koja pali svjetiljku,
imbue it with color
ispunjava je bojom
and disappear in a firework of flames.
i nestaje u vatrometu.
But you either bring a letter or you write one there,
Ali možeš donijeti pismo ili ga napisati tamo
and you burn it.
pa spaliti.
And of course we know intuitively what is on those letters and postcards.
A intuitivno naravno znamo što piše u tim pismima i na tim razglednicama.
It's a form of affection and love that is now no longer extant, yeah?
To je oblik privrženosti i ljubavi koja više ne postoji, zar ne?
And then the third ritual:
A zatim treći ritual:
between all these fires are large piles of clothes.
između tih ognjišta velike su hrpe odjeće.
And you leave an item of clothing
Ostavite odjevni predmet
that has helped you to get to this place.
koji vam je pomogao stići.
And I said to Marlene, "What did you leave at the cliff edge?"
Pitao sam Marlene: "Što si ostavila na rubu litice?"
She said, "I left my boots --
Rekla je: "Ostavila sam čizme --
the very things that I walked in, actually.
upravo one u kojima sam došla.
They were beautiful boots, I loved those boots,
To su bile prekrasne čizme, obožavala sam ih,
but they were finished after seven weeks of walking.
ali bile su gotove nakon sedam tjedana hoda.
So I walked away in my trainers,
Stoga sam otišla u tenisicama,
but I left my boots there."
a čizme sam ostavila tamo."
She said, "It was really incredible.
Rekla je: "Bilo je nevjerojatno.
The most powerful moment was, the sun was going down,
Najsnažniji trenutak bio je kada je sunce zalazilo,
but the full moon was coming up behind me.
a pun mjesec izlazio je iza mene.
And the full moon was illuminated by the dying sun in such a powerful way
Pun mjesec bio je osvijetljen zalazećim suncem na tako moćan način
that even after the sun had dropped below the horizon,
da je čak i nakon što je zašlo iza obzora,
the moon could still see that sun.
mjesec i dalje vidio to sunce.
And I had a moon shadow,
Imala sam sjenu od mjeseca,
and I was looking at my moon shadow walking across the Atlantic,
i gledala sam svoju mjesečevu sjenu kako ide preko Atlantika,
across this ocean.
preko tog oceana.
And I thought,
I pomislila sam:
'Oh! That's my new self going into the future.'
"O pa to sam nova ja koja odlazim u budućnost."
But suddenly I realized the sun was falling further.
Odjedanput sam shvatila da sunce i dalje zalazi.
The moon was losing its reflection,
Mjesec je gubio odsjaj,
and my shadow was disappearing.
a moja je sjena nestajala.
The most powerful moment I had on the whole Camino
Najsnažniji trenutak koji sam doživjela u Caminu
was when I realized I myself had to walk across that unknown sea
bio je kada sam shvatila da moram prijeći to nepoznato more
into my future."
prema svojoj budućnosti."
Well, I was so taken by this story,
Toliko me obuzela ta priča
I wrote this piece for her.
da sam napisao pjesmu za nju.
We were driving at the time;
Vozili smo se;
we got home, I sat on the couch,
došli smo kući, sjeo sam na kauč
I wrote until two in the morning --
i pisao do dva ujutro --
everyone had gone to bed --
svi su otišli na spavanje --
and I gave it to Marlene at breakfast time.
i dao sam je Marlene za doručkom.
It's called, "Finisterre," for Marlene McCormack.
Zove se "Finisterre" za Marlene McCormack.
"The road in the end
"Cesta na kraju
the road in the end taking the path the sun had taken
cesta na kraju ide putem sunca
taking the path the run had taken
ide putem hoda
into the western sea
u zapadno more
the road in the end taking the path the sun had taken
cesta na kraju ide putem sunca
into the western sea
u zapadno more
and the moon
a mjesec
the moon rising behind you
mjesec koji se diže iza tebe
as you stood where ground turned to ocean:
dok stojiš na mjestu gdje zemlja postaje ocean:
no way to your future now
sada nema puta prema budućnosti
walking before you across water, going where shadows go,
koja ide ispred tebe preko vode, ide kamo sjene idu,
no way to make sense of a world that wouldn't let you pass
ne može se objasniti svijet koji te ne bi pustio da prođeš
except to call an end to the way you had come,
osim da proglasiš kraj puta kojim dolaziš,
to take out each letter you had brought
izvadiš svako pismo koje donosiš
and light their illumined corners;
i zapališ njegove osvijetljene rubove;
and to read them as they drifted on the late western light;
i čitaš dok ga nosi kasno zapadno svjetlo;
to empty your bags
isprazniš torbe
to sort this and to leave that
nešto razvrstaš, a nešto ostaviš
to sort this and to leave that;
nešto razvrstaš, a nešto ostaviš;
to promise what you needed to promise all along
obećaš ono što si davno trebao
to promise all along,
obećaš ono što si davno trebao,
and to abandon the shoes that brought you here
i napustiš cipele kojima si došao
right at the water's edge,
tamo na obali,
not because you had given up
ne zato što odustaješ
but because now,
već zato što sada
you would find a different way to tread,
znaš drugi put kojim bi išao,
and because, through it all,
i zato što nakon svega,
part of you would still walk on,
dio tebe želi ići dalje,
no matter how,
na bilo koji način,
over the waves."
preko valova."
"Finisterre."
"Finisterre."
For Marlene McCormack --
Za Marlene McCormack --
(Applause)
(Pljesak)
who has already had her third play performed
čija je treća predstava izvedena
in off-off-off-off-Broadway --
u alternativnom alternativnom kazalištu --
in Dublin.
u Dublinu.
(Laughter)
(Smijeh)
But she's on her way.
Ali slijedi svoj put.
This is the last piece.
Ovo je zadnje djelo.
This is about the supposed arrival at the sum of all of our endeavors.
Ovo je pretpostavljeno ostvarenje svih naših nastojanja.
In Santiago itself --
Dolazak u sam Santiago --
it could be Santiago,
to može biti Santiago,
it could be Mecca,
može biti Meka,
it could be Varanasi,
može biti Benares,
it could be Kyoto,
može biti Kyoto,
it could be that threshold you've set for yourself,
može biti granica koju ste si postavili,
the disturbing approach to the consummation of all your goals.
uznemirujuć pristup ispunjenju svih ciljeva.
And one of the difficulties about walking into your life,
A jedna od teškoća kod ulaska u život,
about coming into this body,
ulaska u tijelo,
into this world fully,
potpuno u svijet,
is you start to realize
jest kada shvatite
that you have manufactured three abiding illusions
da ste proizveli tri trajne iluzije
that the rest of humanity has shared with you since the beginning of time.
koje čovječanstvo dijeli otpočetka svijeta.
And the first illusion is that you can somehow construct a life
Prva je iluzija da nekako stvarate život
in which you are not vulnerable.
u kojem niste ranjivi.
You can somehow be immune to all of the difficulties
Na neki način možete biti imuni na sve poteškoće
and ill health and losses
i bolesti i gubitke
that humanity has been subject to since the beginning of time.
kojima je čovječanstvo podložno otpočetka svijeta.
If we look out at the natural world,
Ako pogledamo prirodni svijet,
there's no part of that world
nema niti jednog njegovog dijela
that doesn't go through cycles of, first, incipience,
koji ne ide kroz cikluse: prvo je početak
or hiddenness,
ili skrivenost,
but then growth, fullness,
zatim rast, potpunost,
but then a beautiful, to begin with, disappearance,
za početak, prekrasno nestajanje,
and then a very austere, full disappearance.
a zatim vrlo surovo, potpuno nestajanje.
We look at that, we say, "That's beautiful,
Gledamo u to i kažemo: "To je prekrasno,
but can I just have the first half of the equation, please?
ali mogu li dobiti samo prvi dio jednadžbe?
And when the disappearance is happening,
A kada dođe do nestajanja,
I'll close my eyes and wait for the new cycle to come around."
zatvorit ću oči i čekati sljedeći ciklus."
Which means most human beings are at war with reality
Što znači da većina ljudi ratuje sa stvarnošću
50 percent of the time.
50 posto svog vremena.
The mature identity
Zreli identitet
is able to live in the full cycle.
može živjeti u punom krugu.
The second illusion is,
Druga je iluzija
I can construct a life in which I will not have my heart broken.
da mogu izgraditi život u kojem moje srce neće biti slomljeno.
Romance is the first place we start to do it.
Zaljubljenost je prva točka.
When you're at the beginning of a new romance or a new marriage,
Kada ste na početku nove veze ili novog braka,
you say, "I have found the person who will not break my heart."
govorite: "Pronašao sam osobu koja mi neće slomiti srce."
I'm sorry;
Žao mi je:
you have chosen them out unconsciously for that exact core competency.
odabrali ste ju nesvjesno upravo zbog te sposobnosti.
(Laughter)
(Smijeh)
They will break your heart.
Slomit će vam srce.
Why?
Zašto?
Because you care about them.
Zato što vam je stalo do nje.
You look at parenting, yeah?
Pogledajmo roditeljstvo.
Parenting: "I will be the perfect mother and father."
Roditeljstvo: "Bit ću savršena majka, savršen otac."
Your children will break your heart.
Djeca će vam slomiti srce.
And they don't even have to do anything spectacular or dramatic.
A ne moraju nužno učiniti ništa spektakularno ni dramatično.
But usually, they do do something spectacular or dramatic --
Obično učine nešto spektakularno ili dramatično...
(Laughter)
(Smijeh)
to break your heart.
i slome vam srce.
And then they live with you as spies and saboteurs for years,
I žive s vama kao špijuni ili saboteri godinama,
watching your every psychological move,
prate svaki vaš psihološki korak,
and spotting your every weakness.
i uočavaju svaku vašu slabost.
And one day,
I jednog dana,
when they're about 14 years old,
kada napune 14 godina,
with your back turned to them,
dok ste im okrenuti leđima
in the kitchen,
u kuhinji,
while you're making something for them --
dok im nešto pripremate --
(Laughter)
(Smijeh)
the psychological stiletto goes in.
psihološki nož dolazi na scenu.
(Applause)
(Pljesak)
And you say, "How did you know exactly where to place it?"
Pitate: "Kako si znao kamo ubosti?"
(Laughter)
(Smijeh)
And they say,
A on kaže:
"I've been watching you for --
"Pratim te već --
(Laughter)
(Smijeh)
a good few years."
nekoliko godina."
And then we hope that our armored, professional personalities
Zatim se nadamo da smo stvorili profesionalni oklop
will prevent us from having our heart broken in work.
koji će nas zaštititi od slomljenog srca na poslu.
But if you're sincere about your work,
Ali ako ste iskreni u svom poslu,
it should break your heart.
trebao bi vam slomiti srce.
You should get to thresholds
Trebate doći do granica
where you do not know how to proceed.
gdje ne znate kako dalje.
You do not know how to get from here to there.
Ne znate kako doći od točke A do točke B.
What does that do?
Čemu to služi?
It puts you into a proper relationship with reality.
Stavlja vas u ispravan odnos sa stvarnošću.
Why?
Zašto?
Because you have to ask for help.
Zato što morate tražiti pomoć.
Heartbreak.
Slomljeno srce.
We don't have a choice about heartbreak,
Nemamo izbora oko slomljenog srca,
we only have a choice of having our hearts broken
imamo samo izbor da nam srce slome
over people and things and projects that we deeply care about.
ljudi i stvari i projekti za koje marimo.
And the last illusion is,
A zadnja je iluzija
I can somehow plan enough and arrange things
da mogu dovoljno planirati i organizirati
that I will be able to see the path to the end
tako da vidim cestu do kraja
right from where I'm standing,
upravo s ovog mjesta na kojem stojim,
right to the horizon.
sve do obzora.
But when you think about it,
Ali kada razmislite malo,
the only environment in which that would be true
jedino okruženje u kojemu to može biti tako
would be a flat desert,
jest ravna pustinja,
empty of any other life.
bez ikakvog oblika života.
But even in a flat desert,
No čak i u praznoj pustinji,
the curvature of the earth would take the path away from you.
zaobljenost zemlje oduzela bi vam put.
So, no;
Stoga, ne;
you see the path,
vidite put,
and then you don't
a zatim više ne,
and then you see it again.
zatim ga opet vidite.
So this is "Santiago,"
To je, dakle, "Santiago",
the supposed arrival,
pretpostavljeni dolazak,
which is a kind of return to the beginning all at the same time.
koji je istovremeno oblik povratka na početak.
We have this experience of the journey,
Imamo doživljaj putovanja,
which is in all of our great spiritual traditions,
koji se pojavljuje u svim duhovnim tradicijama,
of pilgrimage.
hodočašća.
But just by actually standing in the ground of your life fully,
Ali ako potpuno stojite na zemlji
not trying to abstract yourself into a strategic future
i ne pokušavate se strateški dohvatiti budućnosti,
that's actually just an escape from present heartbreak;
to je zapravo samo bijeg od slomljenog srca u sadašnjosti;
the ability to stand in the ground of your life
mogućnost stajanja na zemlji
and to look at the horizon that is pulling you --
i gledanja u obzor koji vas privlači...
in that moment,
u tom trenutku,
you are the whole journey.
vi ste cijelo putovanje.
You are the whole conversation.
Vi ste cijeli razgovor.
"Santiago."
"Santiago".
"The road seen, then not seen
"Cesta koju vidiš pa ne vidiš
the road seen, then not seen
cesta koju vidiš pa ne vidiš
the hillside hiding then revealing the way you should take
brdo koje skriva pa otkriva put kojim moraš ići
the road seen, then not seen
cesta koju vidiš pa ne vidiš
the hillside hiding then revealing the way you should take,
brdo koje skriva pa otkriva put kojim moraš ići,
the road dropping away from you
cesta koja te odvlači od tebe
as if leaving you to walk on thin air,
kao da te stavlja na tanak led,
then catching you,
zatim hvata,
catching you,
hvata,
holding you up, when you thought you would fall,
zadržava kad pomisliš da padaš,
catching you,
hvata,
holding you up, when you thought you would fall,
zadržava kad pomisliš da padaš,
and the way forward
a put prema naprijed
the way forward always in the end
put prema naprijed uvijek na kraju
the way that you came,
put kojim si došao,
the way that you followed, the way that carried you into your future,
put koji si slijedio put koji te nosi u budućnost,
that brought you to this place,
koji te doveo ovamo,
no matter that it sometimes had to take your promise from you,
bez obzira što je ponekad tražio obećanja,
no matter that it always had to break your heart along the way:
bez obzira što uvijek lomi tvoje srce;
the sense
osjećaj
the sense of having walked from deep inside yourself
osjećaj da si došao iz dubine sebe
out into the revelation,
u otkrivenje,
to have risked yourself
da si se doveo u opasnost
for something that seemed to stand both inside you and far beyond you,
radi nečega što je postojalo u tebi i daleko izvan tebe,
and that called you back in the end
i što te dovelo natrag na kraju
to the only road you could follow,
na jedini put kojim možeš ići,
walking as you did, in your rags of love
dok hodaš kao uvijek u dronjcima ljubavi
and speaking in the voice that by night became a prayer for safe arrival,
i govoriš glasom koji noću postaje molitva za siguran uspjeh,
so that one day
tako da jednog dana
one day you realized
jednog dana shvatiš
that what you wanted had actually already happened
da se sve što si želio već ostvarilo
one day you realized
jednog dana shvatiš
that what you wanted had actually already happened
da se sve što si želio već ostvarilo
and long ago
i to davno
and in the dwelling place in which you lived before you began,
i na mjestu na kojem si prije živio, s kojeg si krenuo
and that
i da
and that every step along the way,
i da si svakim korakom
every step along the way,
svakim korakom
you had carried the heart and the mind and the promise
nosio srce i um i obećanje
that first set you off and then drew you on,
koji su te pokrenuli i održavali
and that
i da
and that you were more marvelous
i da si bio čarobniji
in your simple wish to find a way
u jednostavnoj želji da pronađeš put
you were more marvelous
bio si čarobniji
than the gilded roofs of any destination you could reach
od pozlaćenih krovova bilo kojeg odredišta
you were more marvelous in that simple wish to find a way
bio si čarobniji u jednostavnoj želji da pronađeš put
than the gilded roofs of any destination you could reach:
od pozlaćenih krovova bilo kojeg odredišta:
as if, all along,
kao da si cijelim putem
you had thought the end point might be a city with golden domes,
mislio da je krajnji cilj grad sa zlatnim kupolama,
and cheering crowds,
i razdragano mnoštvo,
and turning the corner
a kad si skrenuo iza ugla
at what you thought was the end of the road,
tamo gdje si mislio da je kraj puta,
you found just a simple reflection,
stajao je jednostavan odraz,
and a clear revelation beneath the face looking back
i jasno otkrivenje ispod lica koja te gleda,
and beneath it another invitation,
i ispod toga još jedan poziv,
all in one glimpse
sve u jednom pogledu
all in one glimpse:
sve u jednom pogledu:
like a person
poput osobe
like a person or a place you had sought forever
poput osobe ili mjesta koje oduvijek tražiš
you had sought forever,
koje oduvijek tražiš,
like a bold field of freedom that beckoned you beyond;
poput hrabrog polja slobode koje te doziva;
like another life
poput drugog života
like another life,
poput drugog života,
and the road
a cesta
the road still stretching on."
cesta nastavlja dalje."
(Applause)
(Pljesak)
Thank you.
Hvala.
Thank you very much. Thank you.
Puno hvala. Hvala.
You're very kind. Thank you.
Jako ste dragi. Hvala.
(Applause)
(Pljesak)